<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A speech delivered by Sir Francis Bacon, in the lower House of Parliament quinto Iacobi, concerning the article of naturalization of the Scottish nation.</title>
            <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76885</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E158_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20938</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868259</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868259</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76885)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 28:E158[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A speech delivered by Sir Francis Bacon, in the lower House of Parliament quinto Iacobi, concerning the article of naturalization of the Scottish nation.</title>
                  <author>Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed Anno, 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156900:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156900:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SPEECH DELIVERED BY Sir Francis Bacon, In the lower Houſe of Parliament <hi>quinto</hi> IACOBI, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Article of <hi>Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation</hi> of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed <hi>Anno,</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:156900:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156900:2"/>
            <head>A SPEECH Vſed by Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> in the lower Houſe of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, quinto</hi> Jacobi, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Article of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalization</hi> of the <hi>Scottiſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may pleaſe you (Maſter Speaker) preface will I uſe none, but put my ſelfe upon your good opinions, to which I have beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed beyond my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervings, neither will I hold you in ſuſpence, what way I will chuſe, but now at the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my ſelfe, that I meane to counſell the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:156900:3"/>Houſe to Naturalize this Nation, wherein ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe I have a requeſt to make unto you, which is of more efficacy to the purpoſe I have in hand, than all that I ſhall ſay afterwards: And it is the ſame requeſt, which <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> did more then once, in great cauſes of eſtate, make to the people of <hi>Athens,</hi> That when they took into their hands the Balls, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to give their voices (according as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of them was) they would raiſe their thoughts, and lay aſide thoſe conſiderations, which their private vacations and degrees might miniſter and repreſent unto them, and would take upon them, cogitations and minds agreeable to the dignity and honour of the eſtate.</p>
            <p>For (Maſter Speaker) as it was aptly and ſharply ſaid by <hi>Alexander</hi> to <hi>Parmenio,</hi> when upon their recitall of the great offers which <hi>Darius</hi> made, <hi>Parmenio</hi> ſaid unto him, I would accept theſe offers, were I as <hi>Alexander,</hi> hee turned it upon him againe, ſo would I (ſaith hee) were I as <hi>Parmenio,</hi> ſo in this cauſe: if an honeſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant (I doe not ſingle out that State in diſgrace, for this Iſland ever held it honourable, but only for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a private profeſsion) If an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant ſhould ſay, ſurely I would proceed no further in the union, were I as the King, it might bee reaſonably anſwered, no more
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156900:3"/>would the King, were he as an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant; and the like may be ſaid of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the Country, bee he never ſo worthy or ſufficient, or of a Lawyer be hee never ſo wiſe or learned, or of any other particular condition in this Kingdome, for certainly (Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Speaker) if a man ſhall be only or chiefly ſenſible of thoſe reſpects which his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affection, and degree ſhall ſuggeſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe into him, and not enter into true and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy conſiderations of eſtate, he ſhall never be able aright to give counſell, or take counſell in this matter, for that if this requeſt be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I account the cauſe obtained.</p>
            <p>But to proceed to the matter it ſelf; all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations do reſt upon queſtions comparative, for when a queſtion is <hi>de vero,</hi> it is ſimple, for there is but one truth, but when a queſtion is <hi>de bono,</hi> it is for the moſt part comparative, for there be differing degrees of good and evill, and the beſt of the good is to be preferred and choſen, and the worſt of the evill is to be declined and avoided, and therefore in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of this nature, you may not looke for anſwer, proper to every inconvenience allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, for ſomewhat that cannot be ſpecially anſwered, may nevertheleſſe be encountred, and overweighed by matter of greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore, for the matter which I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156900:4"/>ſhall ſet forth unto you, will naturally receive the diſtribution of three parts.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">The anſwer to the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</note> an anſwer to theſe inconveniences which have beene alleaged to enſue, if wee ſhould give way to this Naturalization, which I ſuppoſe you will not finde to bee, which I ſuppoſe will not be ſo great, as they have bin made, but that much droſſe is put into the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, to help to make weight.</p>
            <p>Secondly, an encounter againſt the remayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of theſe inconveniences, which cannot properly be anſwered, by much greater incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, which wee ſhall incurre, if wee doe not proceed to this Naturalization.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, an encounter likewiſe, but of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other nature, that is by the gaine and benefit, which wee ſhall draw and purchaſe to our ſelves by proceeding to this Naturalization. And yet to avoid confuſion, which ever fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth of too much generality, it is neceſſary for me (before I proceed to perſwaſion) to uſe ſome diſtribution of the points or parts of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalization, which certainly can be no better, or none other, than the ancient diſtinction of <hi>jus Civitatis, jus ſuffragii vel tribus, Jus Petitionis ſive honoris:</hi> for all ability and capacitie is either of private intereſt, of <hi>Meum &amp; Tuum,</hi> or of publike ſervice, and the publike conſiſteth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156900:4"/>chiefly either in voice or in office, now it is the firſt of theſe (Maſter Speaker) that I will only handle at this time, and in this place, and referre the other two for a Committee, becauſe they receive more diſtinction and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction.</p>
            <p>To come to the inconveniences alleaged on the other part, the firſt of them is, that their may enſue of this Naturalization, a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of people upon this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> which is ſuppoſed already, to have the full charge and contentment, and therefore there cannot be an admiſſion of the adoptive, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a diſmiſſion of the former times, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of all thoſe, that are native ſubjects of this Realm. A grave objection, (Maſter Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker) and very dutifull, for it proceeds not, of any unkindneſſe to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation, but of a naturall faſtneſſe to our ſelves, for that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of the Virgins, <hi>Ne forte non ſufficiat vobis &amp; nobis,</hi> proceeds not out of any envy, or maligne humour, but out of providence, and the originall charity, which begins with our ſelves, and I muſt confeſſe (M. Speaker) that as the Gentleman ſaid, when <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> in regard of the greatneſſe of their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, grew pent, and ſtraitned, It is true, that though they were brethren, they grew to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and to thoſe words, <hi>Vade tu ad dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:156900:5"/>&amp; ego ad ſiniſtram;</hi> But certainly, I ſhould never have brought that example on that ſide, for wee ſee what followed of it, how this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration <hi>ad dextram &amp; ad ſiniſtram,</hi> Cauſed the miſerable captivity of the one brother, and the dangerous though proſperous war of the other, for his reſcue and recovery.</p>
            <p>But to this objection, (Maſter Speaker) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo weighty, and ſo principall, I meane to give three ſeverall anſwers, every one of them being to my underſtanding by it ſelfe Sufficient.</p>
            <p>The firſt is,
<note place="margin">The opinion of the number of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scottiſh Nation.</note> that the opinion, of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation, that ſhould be likely to plant themſelves here amongſt us, will bee found to bee a thing, rather in conceit then in event, for (Maſter Speaker) you ſhall finde theſe plauſible ſimilitudes of a tree, that will thrive the better, if it bee remooved into the more fruitfull ſoile, and of ſheepe or cattell, that if they finde a gap or paſſage open, will leave the more barren paſture, and get into the more rich and plentifull, to be but argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments meerely ſuperficiall, and to have no ſound reſemblance, with the tranſplanting or transferring of families, for the tree we know by nature, as ſoone as it is ſet in the better ground, can faſten upon it, and take nutriment from it, and a ſheep as ſoone as he gets into
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156900:5"/>the better paſture, what ſhould let him to graſe or feed, But there belongeth more I take it, to a family or particular perſon, that ſhall remove from one Nation to another, for if (Maſter Speaker) they have not ſtock, meanes, acquaintance, and cuſtome, habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, trades, countenance, and the like, I hope you doubt not, but they will ſtarve in the midſt of the rich paſture, and are farre enough from grazing at their pleaſure, and therefore in this point, which is conjecturall,
<note place="margin">Conjecturall experience.</note> experience is the beſt guide for the time paſt, is a pattern of the time to come, I think no man doubteth (Maſter Speaker) but his Majeſties firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, was the greateſt ſpring-tide for the confluence, and enterance of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now I would fain underſtand in theſe four yeeres ſpace, and the fulneſſe, and ſtrength of the Court and Tide, how many families of the Scotch men, are planted in the Citties, Burroughs and Townes of this Kingdom, for I doe aſſure my ſelfe, then more then ſome perſons of quality, about his Majeſties perſon heere at Court and in <hi>London,</hi> and ſome other inferiour perſons, that have a dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, the returne and certificate, if ſuch a Survey ſhould bee made, would be of a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber extreamely ſmall, I report mee to all your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156900:6"/>private knowledges of the places where you inhabite.</p>
            <p>Now (Maſter Speaker) as I ſaid, <hi>Si in ligno vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridi ita fit, quid fiet in arido,</hi> I am ſure there will be no more ſuch ſpring tides; but you will tell me of a multitude of families of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Polania,</hi> and if they multiply in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſo farre, how much more at hand, for that (Maſter Speaker) you muſt impute it of neceſſity to ſome ſpeciall accident of time and prace that draws the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thether: for you ſee plainly before your eys, that in <hi>Geneva,</hi> which is much neerer, where in <hi>France</hi> they are invited with priviledges, and with the very priviledge of naturalization, yet no ſuch number can bee found, ſo as it cannot either bee neerenes of place, or priviledge of perſon that is the cauſe. But ſhall I tell you (Maſter Speaker) what I thinke; In all the places of the world, neere or farre of, they will never take that courſe of life in this Kingdome, which they content themſelves with in <hi>Poland;</hi> for we ſee ir to bee the nature of all men that will rather diſcover poverty abroad then at home; There is never a gentleman, that hath over reached himſelf in expences, and thereby muſt abate his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, but hee will rather travell, and doe it abroad, then at home, and we know well they have good high ſtomacks, and have ever
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156900:6"/>ſtood in ſome tearmes of emulation, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will never live heere except they can live in good faſhion, ſo as I aſſure you (Maſter Speaker) I am of opinion, that the firſt which we now have, to admit them, will have like as that contention had between the Nobility and people of <hi>Rome,</hi> for admitting of a <hi>Plebean</hi> Common-wealth, whilſt it was in paſſage it was very vehement, and mightily ſtood upon, and when the people had obtained it, they never made any <hi>Plebean Conſul,</hi> not in 60 yeers after, and ſo will this be, for many yeers, as I am perſwaded, rather a matter in opinion and reputation, then in effect, and this is the firſt anſwere, that I give to this main inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience pretended of ſurcharge of people.</p>
            <p>The ſecond anſwere,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> not peopled to the full.</note> which I give to this objection is this, I muſt have leave to doubt (Maſter Speaker) that this Realme of <hi>England</hi> is not peopled to the full, for certain it is, that the territories of <hi>France, Italy, Flanders,</hi> and ſome part of <hi>Germany,</hi> doe in equall ſpace of ground, beare and containe, a farre greater quantity of people, if they were muſtered by the Poll, neither can I ſee, that this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is ſo much inferiour, unto thoſe forrain parts in fruitfulneſſe, as it is in population, which makes mee conceive wee have not our full charge; beſides I do ſee manifeſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156900:7"/>us, the badges and tokens, rather of ſcarceneſſe, then of preſſe of people, as drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned grounds, Commons, Waſtes, and the like, which is a plain demonſtration, that howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there may be an overſwelling throng and preſſe of people, here about <hi>London,</hi> which is moſt in our eie, yet the body of the Kingdome is but thin ſowne with people, and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhal compare the ruines and decayes of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Towns in this Realme, with the erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and augmentations of new, cannot but judge that this Realme hath been farre better peopled in former times, it may be in the <hi>Hep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy,</hi> or otherwiſe generally the rule holdeth, The ſmaller the State the greater the populati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Pro rato,</hi> And whether this be true or no, we neede not ſeeke further, then to call to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, how many of us ſerue heere in this place, for deſolate and decayed Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs,</p>
            <p>Againe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mediterrane,</hi> not Maritime Countries ſurcharged with people.</note> (Maſter Speaker) whoſoever loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth into the principle of eſtate, muſt hold, that it is the <hi>Mediterrane</hi> Countries, and not the Maritime which need to feare ſurcharge of people, for all ſea provinces and eſpecially Iſlands have an other element beſides the earth and ſoile, for their ſuſtentation, what an infinite of people are, and may bee ſuſtained by fiſhing, carriage by ſea, and merchandizing,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156900:7"/>wherein I doe again diſcover, that wee are not all prickt by the multitude of people, for if we were, it were not poſſible, wee ſhould relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh, and reſigne, ſuch an infinite benefit of fiſhing, to the Flemming, as it is well knowne wee do, and therefore I ſee, that wee have waſts by Sea, as well as by land, which ſtill is an infallible argument that our induſtry is not awakned, to ſeeke maintenance to any our great charge or preſſe of people. And laſtly, (Maſter Speaker) there was never any Kingdome in this World, had I think, ſo faire and happy means to iſſue and diſcharge them ultitude of their people, as this Kingdom hath, in regard of that deſolate and waſted Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which being a countrey bleſſed with all moſt all the dowryes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as Rivers, Havens, Woods, Quarryes, good Soile, and temperate climate, and now at laſt bleſt under his Majeſty alſo with obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, doth as it were continually call unto us, for our Colonies and Plantations, and ſo I conclude my ſecond anſwere, to this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded inconvenience of ſurcharge of people.</p>
            <p>The third anſwer (Maiſter Speaker) which I give is this, I demande what is the worſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that can follow of your ſurcharge of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, look into it and you ſhall finde it none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſome honourable warre, for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156900:8"/>of their borders, which finde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves pent, upon forraine parts, with incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, which in a warlike Nation, I know not whether I ſhould tearme an inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or noe, for the ſaying is moſt true, though in an other lenſe, <hi>Omne ſolum forti patria.</hi> It was ſpoken of the patience of an exiled man, but it is no leſſe true in the valour of a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Nation, and certainly (Maſter Speaker) I hope I may ſpeake it without offence, that whenſoever we ſhould hold our ſelves worthy, and whenſoever juſt cauſe ſhould bee given, either to recover our ancient rights, or to revenge our late wrongs, or to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the honour of our anceſtors, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the patrimony of our poſterities, wee would never in this manner forget the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations of amplitude and greatneſſe, and fall at variance about profit and reckonings, fitter a great deale for private perſons, then for Parliaments, and Kingdomes, and thus (Maſter Speaker) I leave this firſt obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to ſuch ſatisfactions as you have heard of.</p>
            <p>The ſecond objection is,
<note place="margin">The funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Laws of <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland</hi> are divers and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall.</note> that the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall lawes of theſe Kingdomes, of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> are yet diverſe and ſeverall, nay more that it is declared by the inſtrument, that they ſhall ſo continue; and that there is no intent in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156900:8"/>his Majeſty to make innovation in them, and therefore that it ſhould not bee ſeaſonable, to proceed to this Naturalization, whereby to endow them with our Rights and Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, except they ſhould likewiſe receive, and ſubmit themſelves to our lawes, and this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection likewiſe (Maſter Speaker) I allow to be a weighty objection and worthy to be well anſwered, and diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>The anſwere which I ſhall offer is this,
<note place="margin">The anſwer to the ſecond ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</note> It is true for mine owne part (Maſter Speaker) that I wiſh the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation governed by our Lawes, for I hold our lawes, with ſome reducement, worthy to govern, and it were the World, but this is that which I ſay, and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire therein your attention, That according to true reaſon of eſtate, Naturalization is in order firſt and precedent to union of Lawes, and in nature ſeperable, and in degree a leſſe matter, and not inſeperable from union of Laws, for Naturalization doth but take out the marks of a Forreiner, but union of Lawes makes them entirely as our ſelves, Naturalization ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away ſeperation, but union of lawes doth take away diſtinction, doe wee not ſee (Maſter Speaker) that in the adminiſtration of the World under the great Monarch God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that his Laws are diverſe, one Law in ſpirits, another in bodies, one Law in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions celeſtiall, an other in Elementary, and yet the Creatures are all one maſſe or lump, without any vacuum or ſeperation, doe wee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156900:9"/>not likewiſe ſee in the ſtate of the Church, that amongſt all people, of all languages, and Linages, there is communion of Saints, and that wee are all fellow Citizens, and Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralizants of the heavenly Jeruſalem, And yet neuer the leſſe, divers Eccleſiaſticall Laws, Policies and Heirarchies, according to the ſpeech of that worthy Father, <hi>In veſte varietas ſit, ſciſsura non ſit,</hi> and theſe certainly (Maſter Speaker) as they are the bonds of love they are the more ſpeciall and private bond, and the bond of Naturalization, the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and generall, for the lawes are rather <hi>Figura Reipublicae,</hi> then <hi>forma,</hi> and rather Bonds of perfection, then Bonds of entireneſſe, and therefore we ſee in the experience of our own government, that in the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> all our Statutes and Laws,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Poynings</hi> Laws.</note> ſince <hi>Poynings</hi> Laws, are not in force, and yet we deny them not the benefit of Naturalization, in <hi>Gerſey</hi> and <hi>Jerneſey</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> our common Lawes are not in force, and yet they have the benefit of Naturalization, neither need any man doubt, but that our Lawes and Cuſtomes muſt in ſmall time gather and win upon theirs, for here is the ſeate of the Kingdome, whence come the ſupreame directions of eſtate, here is the Kings perſon and example of which the verſe ſaith,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156900:9"/>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <hi>Regis ad exemplum, totus componitur orbis.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore it is not poſſible, although not by ſolemne and formall acts of eſtates, yet by the ſecret operation of no long time, but they will come under the yoake of our laws, and ſo <hi>Dulcis tractus pari jugo,</hi> and this is the anſwere I give to the ſecond objection.</p>
            <p>The third objection, is ſome inequallity,
<note place="margin">Inequality in the fortunes betweene <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> in the fortunes of theſe two Nations, <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the commixture whereof, there may enſue advantage to them, and loſſe to us, wherein (M. Speaker) it is well that this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence or diſparity conſiſteth, but in the external goods of fortune, for indeed it muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that for the goods of the minde and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy they are <hi>alteri nos,</hi> or our ſelves, for to doe them but right, wee know in their capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and underſtandings, they are a people ingenious, in labour induſtrious, in cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage valiant, in body hard, active, and comely, more might be ſaid, but in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending them, we doe but in effect, commend our ſelves, for they are of one part, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent with us, and the truth is, we are partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant, both of their vertue, and vices, for if they have beene noted, to be a people not ſoe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable in government, we cannot without flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156900:10"/>our ſelves, free our ſelves altogether from that fault, being indeed incident to all martiall people, as wee ſee it evident by the example of the Romans, and others, even like unto fierce horſes, that though they be of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſervice then others, yet are they harder to guide and manage.</p>
            <p>But for this objection (Maſter Speaker) I purpoſe to anſwere it, not by the authority of Scriptares, which ſaith, <hi>Beatius eſt dare quam accipere,</hi> But an authority, framed and derived from the judgment of our ſelves, and our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors in the ſame caſe; as to the point, for (Maſter Speaker) in all the lives of our Kings, none uſeth to carry greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation then his Majeſties noble progenitor King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt of that name, and amongſt his other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendations, both of warre and policie, none is more celebrated, then his purpoſe and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, for that conqueſt of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as not ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his deſignes, to glorious acqueſts abroad, but to ſolid ſtrength at home, which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe if it had ſucceeded, could not but have brought in all theſe inconveniences, of the commixture of a more opulent Kingdome, with a leſſe,
<note place="margin">Laws nor Arms cannot alter the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of climats.</note> that are now alledged, for it is not the yoake, either of our lawes or armes, that can alter the nature of the Climate, or the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ſoil, neither is it the manner of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156900:10"/>the Commixture, that can alter the nature of Commixture, and therefore (Maſter Speaker) if it were good for us then, it is good for us now, and not to be prized the leſſer, becauſe we payed not ſo deare for it. But a more full objection, I refer over to that, which will come after, to bee ſpoken touching ſurety, and greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>The fourth Objection (Maſter Speaker) is not properly an objection but rather a preoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation of an objection of the other ſide, for it may bee ſaid and very materially, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts wee doe contend, the benefit of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralization is by the Law, in as many as have beene, or ſhall bee borne, ſince his Majeſties comming to the Crown, already ſetled and inveſted, there is no more then, but to bring the <hi>Ante-nati,</hi> into the degree of the <hi>Poſt-nati,</hi> that men grown, that have well deſerved, may bee in no worſe caſe, then children which have not deſerved, and elder brothers in no worſe caſe, then younger brothers, ſo as wee ſtand upon <hi>quiddam non quantum,</hi> being but a little difference of time, of one generation from an other, to this (M. Speaker) it is ſaid by ſome, that the Law is not ſo but that the <hi>poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati</hi> are aliens as the reſt. A pointe, that I mean not much to argue, both becauſe it hath been well ſpoken, by the gentleman that ſpoke laſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156900:11"/>before mee, and becauſe I doe deſire in this caſe, and in this place, to ſpeak rather of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencie, then of Law, only this I will ſay, that, that opinion ſeems to mee contrary to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Law, and contrary to Authority, and experience of Law; for reaſon of Law, when I meditate of it, my thinks the wiſdome of the Common Lawes of <hi>England</hi> well obſerved, is admirable in the diſtribution of the benefit and protection of the Laws, according to the ſeveral conditions of perſons in an excellent proportion, the degrees are foure, but bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partite; two of Aliens, and two of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p>The firſt degree is of an alien borne under a King,
<note place="margin">The firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of an alien.</note> or State, that is enemy, if ſuch an one come into this Kingdom without ſafe conduct, it is at his perrill, the Law giveth him no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection neither for Body, Lands, nor Goods, ſo as if hee be ſlaine, there is no remedy by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny appeale at the parties ſuit although the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were an <hi>Engliſh</hi> woman, marry at the Kings ſuit, the caſe may bee otherwiſe in reguard of the offence, to the peace, and Crown.</p>
            <p>The ſecond degree is of an alien that is born under the faith and alleigeance of a King or ſtate,
<note place="margin">The ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien born un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a State, that is Friend.</note> that is a friend, unto ſuch a perſon, the Law doth imparte a great benefit and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156900:11"/>that is concerning things perſonall, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory and moveable, as goods and chattells, contracts and the like, but not concerning freehold and Inheritance, and the reaſon is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee may be an enemy, though he be not; for the State under the obeyſance of which hee is may enter into quarrell, and hoſtility, and therefore as the Law, hath but a tranſitory aſſurance of him, ſo it rewards him, but with tranſitory benefits.</p>
            <p>The third degree is of a ſubject who having beene an alien is by charter and deniſation,
<note place="margin">The third de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien ſubject.</note> to ſuch an one, the law doth imparte, yet a more ample benefit, for it gives him power to purchaſe freehold and inheritance to his owne uſe, and likewiſe to enable thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, borne after his denization to inherit, but nevertheleſſe hee cannot make title, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey pedigree from any anceſtors peramount, for the Law thinks not good to make him in the ſame degree, with a ſubject born, becauſe hee was once an alien, and ſo might once have beene an Enemy, <hi>Et nemo ſubito fingitur,</hi> affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons cannot be ſetled by any benefit, as when from their Nativity, they are imbred, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent.</p>
            <p>And the fourth degree,
<note place="margin">The fourth degree the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect degree.</note> which is the perfect
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156900:12"/>degree, is of ſuch a perſon, as neither is enemy, nor can be enemy in time to come, nor would have beene enemy in time paſt, nor can bee enemy in time to come, therefore the Law gives unto him, the full benefit of Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation.</p>
            <p>Now (Maſter Speaker) if theſe be true ſteps and paces of the Law; no man can deny, but whoſoever is borne under the Kings obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence never could <hi>in aliquo puncto temporis</hi> bee an enemy, and therefore in reaſon of Law, is natural, Nay, contrariwiſe, he is bound <hi>Jure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitatis</hi> to defend this Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> againſt all Innovators and Rebells, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as hee is obliged to the protection of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liens, and that perpetually, and univerſally, ſo he is to have that perpetuall and univerſall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and protection of lawes which is Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralization.</p>
            <p>For forme of pleading it is true that hath beene ſaid, that if a man, would pleade an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be an alien, he muſt not only ſet forth negatively, and primitively, that hee was born out of the obedience of our Soveraine Lord the King, but affirmatively, under the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſe of a forraine King, or ſtate, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, which never can bee done in this caſe.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:156900:12"/>
            <p>As for authority, I will not preſſe it, you know all what hath beene publiſhed by the Kings Proclamation, and for experience of Lawes, wee ſee it in the ſubjects of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the Subjects of <hi>Gernſey,</hi> and <hi>Ierneſey,</hi> parcels of the Duchy of <hi>Normandy,</hi> in the Subjects of <hi>Callis,</hi> when it was <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which was parcel of the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> But as I ſaid, I am not willing to enter into an argument of Law, but to hold my ſelfe to point of conveniencie, ſo as for my part, I hold all, <hi>Naturales ipſo jure,</hi> But yet I am farr from opinion, that it ſhould be a thing ſuperfluous to have it done by.</p>
            <p>Chiefely in reſpect of that true principall of State, <hi>Principum actiones ad famam ſunt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponendae,</hi> It will lift up a ſigne to all the World, of our Loves towards them, and good agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with them, and theſe are (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Speaker, the materiall objections, which have beene on the other ſide, whereunto you have heard my anſweres, weigh them in your wiſdomes, and ſo I conclude that generall part.</p>
            <p>Now (Maſter Speaker) according as I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed I muſt fill the other ballance, in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing unto you the inconveniences, which wee ſhall incur, if we ſhall not proceed to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalization, wherein that convenience above all others, and alone by it ſelfe, if there were
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156900:13"/>none other, doth exceedingly moove mee, and may moove you, is a poſition of eſtate, colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of the Records of time, which is this, That whatſoever ſeverall Kingdomes or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, have bene united in Soverainty, if that union hath not beene fortified, and bound in with a further union, and namely that which is now in queſtion (of Naturalization) this hath followed, that at one time or other, they have broken, being upon all occaſions apt to relaps and revolt to the former Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Of this aſſertion, The firſt example which I will ſet before you, is of the memorable U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<note place="margin">The union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and the <hi>Latins.</hi>
               </note> which was betweene the Romans and the Latins, which continued from the Battell at the Lake of <hi>Regilla,</hi> for many yeeres unto the Conſulſhip.</p>
            <p>At what time, their began about this very point of Naturalization, that warr which was called <hi>Bellum Sociale,</hi> being the moſt bloody and pernitious warre, that ever the Romane State endured, wherein after numbers of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, and infinite ſieges and ſurpriſes of Towns, the Romanes in the end prevailed, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred the Latins, And ever as they held the honour of the warre, ſo looking back into what perdition and confuſion, they were near
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156900:13"/>to have beene brought, they preſently natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralized them all, you ſpeake of a naturalization in blood, there was a naturalization indeed in blood.</p>
            <p>Let me ſet before you againe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sparta</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loponcſus.</hi>
               </note> the example of <hi>Sparta</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Peneloponeſus</hi> their aſſociates. The State of <hi>Sparta,</hi> was a nice and jealous ſtate of this point of imparting na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalization to their confederates. But what was the iſſue of it, after they held them in a kind of ſociety and amity for diversyeers, upon the firſt occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> given which was no more then the ſurpriſall of the Caſtle of <hi>Thebes,</hi> by certaine deſperate conſpirators in the habit of Maſters, there enſued imediately a general revolt &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of their aſſociates, which was the ruine of their State never afterwards to be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
            <p>Of latter times,
<note place="margin">The Union of the Kingdome of <hi>Arragon.</hi>
               </note> Let me lead your conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to behold the like events in the Kingdom of <hi>Arragon,</hi> which Kingdom was united with <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the perſons of <hi>Ferdinando,</hi> and <hi>Iſabella,</hi> and ſo continued many years, but yet ſo as it ſtood a Kingdome ſevered and devided from the reſt of <hi>Spaine</hi> in priviledges, and directly in this point of Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralization, or capacity of inheritance, what came of this, Thus much, that now of freſh
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156900:14"/>memory, not paſt twelve yeeres ſince, onely upon the voice of a condemned man, out of the grate of a priſon, towards the ſtreete, that cried <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> which is as much as Liberties or Priviledges, there was raiſed a dangerous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, which was ſuppreſſed with difficulty with an army Royall, and their priviledges diſanulled, and they incorporated, with the reſt of <hi>Spaine,</hi> upon ſo ſmall a ſparke, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo long continuance, were ready to break, and ſever again.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of the State of <hi>Florence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Florence</hi> and <hi>Piſa.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Piſa,</hi> which City of <hi>Piſa</hi> being united unto <hi>Florence,</hi> but not endued with the benefit of Naturalization, upon the firſt ſight of forraine aſſiſtance,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth.</note> by the expedition of <hi>Charles</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> did revolte, though it bee ſince againe reunited, and incorporated.</p>
            <p>The ſame effect wee ſee in the moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Government,
<note place="margin">The like ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> which ſhewes it the rather to bee an effect of nature, for it was thought a fit policy by the councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to retaine the Provinces of <hi>Tranſylvania, Valachia,</hi> and <hi>Moldavia,</hi> which were as the nurſes of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> in reſpect of their proviſions, to the end they might bee the leſſe waſted, onely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Vayvods,</hi> as Vaſſals and <hi>Homagers,</hi> and not under <hi>Baſhaws,</hi> as Provinces of the <hi>Yurkiſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156900:14"/>w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> policy we ſee by late experience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unfortuuate, as appeared by the revolt of the ſame three Provinces, under the Armies &amp; Conduct of <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi> a leader very famous for a time, which revolt is not yet fully recovered, whereas we ſeldome or never hear of revolts of Provinces incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire.</p>
            <p>On the other part (Maſter Speaker) becauſe it is true, which the Logicians ſay, <hi>Oppoſita jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſe poſita magis,</hi> Let us take a view, and wee ſhall find that whereſoever Kingdomes and States have beene united, and that union incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roberate,
<note place="margin">Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation a ſure bond.</note> by the bond of Naturalization mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, you ſhall never obſerve them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon any occaſion of trouble or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to breake, and ſever againe, as wee ſee moſt evidently before our eies, in our Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>France</hi> that is to ſay <hi>Guyen, Province, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy, Britain,</hi> which notwithſtanding the infinite infeſting troubles of that Kingdome, never offered to breake again.</p>
            <p>We ſee the like effect, in all the Kingdomes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which are mutually Naturalized as <hi>Leon, Caſtile, Valentia, Andaluzia, Granada,</hi> and the reſt, except <hi>Arragon</hi> which held the contrary courſe, and therefore had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156900:15"/>ſucceſſe, as it was ſaid of <hi>Portugall,</hi> of which there is not yet ſufficient triall, and laſtly wee ſee the like effect,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>England</hi> never ſevered after once united.</note> in our own Nation, which never rent aſunder after it was united, ſo as wee now ſcarce know whether the Heptarchy were a Story or a Fable, and therefore (Maſter Speaker) when I revolue with my ſelfe, theſe examples and others, ſo lively expreſſing the neceſſity of a Naturalization to avoid a relaps into a ſeparation, and doe heere ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny arguments and ſcruples on the other ſide, it makes mee think on the old Biſhop which upon a publique diſputation of certaine Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Divines, with ſome learned men of the heathen, did extreamely preſſe to bee heard, and they were loath to ſuffer him, becauſe they knew hee was unlearned, though otherwiſe an holy, and well meaning man, But at laſt, with much adoe hee got to be heard, and when hee came to ſpeake, in ſtead of uſing Argument, he did only ſay over his belief, but did it with ſuch aſſurance and conſtancy, that it did ſtrike the minds of thoſe that heard him, more then any Argument had done, and ſo (Maſter Speaker) againſt all theſe wittie and ſubtile Arguments, I ſay I doe believe, and I would bee ſorry to bee found a prophet in it, that except we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with this Naturalization, though not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in his Majeſties time, who hath ſuch inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156900:15"/>in both nations, yet in the meane time of his Diſcendants, theſe realms will bee in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall danger, to divide and breake again, now if any man bee of that careleſſe minde, <hi>Maneat mors ea, ea cura nepotes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or of that harde minde to leave things to be tried by the ſharpeſt ſword, ſure I am, hee is not of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> opinion, who affirmeth that whoſoever uſeth not fore-ſight and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for his family, is worſe then an unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, much more if wee ſhall not uſe fore-ſight, for theſe two Kingdomes, that comprehend in them ſo many families, but leave things open to the perill of future diviſions, and thus have I expreſſed unto you, what inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, of all others ſinke deepeſt with mee, as the moſt weighty, neither doth their want other inconveniences (Maſter Speaker) the effects and influence whereof, I feare will not bee adjourned to ſo long a day, as this that I have ſpoken of, But I leave it to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and wiſdomes, to conſider, whether you doe not thinke, in caſe by the deniall of this Naturalization, any Pike, alienation, or unkindneſſe, I doe not ſay ſhould bee, but ſhould be thought to bee, or noiſed to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene theſe two Nations, whether it will not quicken or exite, all the envious, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156900:16"/>humours, whereſoever (which are now covered) againſt us, either forraine or at home, and ſo open the way to practice,
<note place="margin">A binding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience.</note> and other Engines, and machinations, to the diſturbance of this State. As for that other inconvenience, it is too binding and too preſſing to be ſpoken of, and may do better a great deale in your mindes then in my mouth, or the mouth of any man elſe, becauſe as I have ſaid it doth preſſe our liberty too farre, and therefore (M. Speaker) I come to this third generall part of my diviſion, concerning the benefit which we ſhall purchaſe, by knitting this knott, ſurer and ſtraiter, betweene theſe two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, by the Communicating of Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation.</p>
            <p>The benefits may appeare to be two, the one ſurety the other greatneſſe, touching ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (Maſter Speaker) it was well ſaid by <hi>Titus Quintus</hi> the <hi>Romane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The benefit of Surety.</note> touching the State of <hi>Pelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneſus,</hi> that the Tortoiſe is ſafe within her ſhell, <hi>Teſtudo inter tegumen tutaeſt,</hi> but if there be any parts that ly open, they endanger all the reſt, wee know well, that although the ſtate at this time bee in a happy peace, yet for the time paſt, the more ancient enemy is the <hi>French,</hi> and the more late the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and both theſe had as it were, their ſeverall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156900:16"/>gates, whereby they might have approach and enterance, to anoy us, <hi>France</hi> had <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Spaine</hi> had <hi>Ireland,</hi> for theſe were but the two acceſſes which did comfort and encourage, both theſe enemies to aſſaile and trouble us, wee ſee that of <hi>Scotland</hi> is cut off, by the Union of theſe two Kingdomes, if that it ſhall bee made conſtant and permanent, that of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is cut off likewiſe by the convenient ſituation of the North of <hi>Scotland,</hi> towards the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where the ſore was, which wee ſee being ſuddenly cloſed by meanes of this ſalve, ſo that as now there are no parts of the State expoſed to danger to bee a temptation to the ambition of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reiners, but their approches and avenues are taken away, for I doe little doubt but theſe Forreners, which had ſo little ſucceſſe, when they had thoſe advantages, will have much leſſe comfort, now that they bee taken from them, and ſoe much for ſurety.</p>
            <p>For greatneſſe (Maſter Speaker) I thinke a man may ſpeake it ſoberly,
<note place="margin">The benefit of greatneſſe.</note> and without bravery, that this Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> having <hi>Scotland</hi> united; <hi>Ireland</hi> reduced, the Sea provinces of the low Countries Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156900:17"/>and ſhipping maintained, is one or the greateſt Monarchies, in forces truly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed, that hath beene in the World, for certainly the Kingdomes heere on earth, have a reſemblance with the Kingdome of Heaven, which our Saviour compareth not to any great Kirnell or nut, but to a very ſmall graine, yet ſuch an one as is apt to grow and ſpread, and ſuch doe I take to be the Conſtitution of this Kingdome, if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed our Countrey bee referred to great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and power, and not quenched too much with the conſideration of utility and wealth, for (M. Speaker) was it not thinke you a true anſwere, that <hi>Solon</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> made to rich King <hi>Croeſus</hi> of <hi>Lydia,</hi> when he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him a great quantity of Gold that hee had gathered together in oſtentation of his greatneſſe and might, but <hi>Solon</hi> ſaid to him contrary to his expectation, why Sir, if an other come that hath better Iron then you, hee will bee Lord of all your Gold; neither is the authority of <hi>Machiavel</hi> to be deſpiſed, who ſcorneth the proverbe of State, taken firſt from a ſpeech of <hi>Mucianus,</hi> that monies are the ſinewes of wars, and ſaith, there are no true ſinews of wars, but the very Armes of valiant men.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:156900:17"/>
            <p>Nay more (Maſter Speaker) whoſoever ſhall look into the ſeminary,
<note place="margin">The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in poverty</note> and beginning of the Monarchie of the world, hee ſhall finde them founded in poverty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perſia</hi> a Countery barren and poore in reſpect of <hi>Media</hi> whom they ſeduced.
<note place="margin">Macedon.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Macedon</hi> a Kingdome ignoble, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary untill <hi>Phillip</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Amintas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rome</hi> had poore and paſtorall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<note place="margin">Rome.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Tuoks</hi> a band of <hi>Sarmathian Scithes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Turks.</hi>
               </note> that in a vagabond maner made impreſsion upon that part of <hi>Aſia</hi> which is called <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comania,</hi> out of which, after much varieties of fortune, ſprung the <hi>Othoman</hi> family now the terror of the World.</p>
            <p>So we know the <hi>Gothes, Vandalls, Alans, Huns, Lombards, Normans,</hi> and the reſt of the Northern people, in one age of the World, made their diſcent and expedition upon the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, and came not as rovers to carry away prey and begun again, but planted themſelves in a number of rich and fruitfull Provinces, where not only
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156900:18"/>their generations, but their names remaine to this day, witneſſe <hi>Lombardy, Catalonia,</hi> a name compounded of <hi>Goth</hi> and <hi>Alan, Andaluzia,</hi> a name corrupted from <hi>Vande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia, Hungaria, Normandy,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>Nay the fortune of the <hi>Swiſſes</hi> of late yeeres,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Switzers.</hi>
               </note> which are bred in a barren and mountenous Countrey, is not to bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, who firſt ruined the duke of <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> the ſame who had almoſt ruined the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> what time after the battell neere <hi>Granſon,</hi> The rich Jewell of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> priſed at many thouſands, was ſold for a few pence, by a common <hi>Swiſse,</hi> that knew no more what a jewell meant, then did <hi>Eſopes</hi> Cock; and againe, the ſame Nation in revenge of a ſcorne was the ruine of the French Kings affaires in <hi>Italy, Lewis</hi> the 12. for that King, when hee was preſſed ſomewhat rudely, by an agent of the <hi>Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> to raiſe their penſions, brake into words of choller, (what ſaith hee) will theſe vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains of the mountain put a taske upon mee, which words loſt him his Duchy of <hi>Millain,</hi> and chaſed him out of <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which examples (Maſter Speaker) doe well prove <hi>Solons</hi> opinion, of the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156900:18"/>and Majeſty that Iron hath over Gold, and therefore if I ſhall ſpeake unto you mine owne heart, me thinkes we ſhould a little disdaine, that the Nation of <hi>Spain,</hi> which howſoever of late it hath begun to rule, yet of ancient time, ſerved many ages, firſt under <hi>Carthage,</hi> then under <hi>Rome,</hi> after under <hi>Saracens, Goths</hi> and others, ſhould of late yeeres take unto them that Spirit, as to dreame of a monarchy in the Weſt, according to that deviſe, <hi>vidi Solem Orientem in Occidente,</hi> onely becauſe they have raiſed, from ſome wild, and unarmed people, Mines and ſtore of Gold, and on the other ſide, that this Iſland of <hi>Britain,</hi> ſeated and named as it is, and that hath, I make no queſtion, the beſt Iron in the World, that is the beſt ſouldiers of the World, ſhall thinke of nothing but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts and audits, and <hi>meum &amp; tuum</hi> and I cannot tell what.</p>
            <p>(Maſter Speaker) I have I take it, gone through the parts which I propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to my ſelfe, wherein if any man ſhall think I have ſung a <hi>placebo,</hi> for mine owne particular, I would have him know that I am not ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene in the world, but that I diſcerne, it were much alike for my private fortune a <hi>tacebo,</hi> as to ſing a <hi>placebo</hi> in this buſineſſe,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156900:19"/>But I have ſpoken out of the Fountain of my heart, <hi>Credidi propter quod locutus ſum,</hi> I believed, therefore I ſpake, ſo as my duty is performed, The Judgments is yours, God direct it for the beſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:156900:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
